Chapter 30: Sources of the Magnetic Field
in the previous chapter we introduced the
concept of the magnetic field
and we focused our attention on the
magnetic field exerting a magnetic
force on a moving charge or a current
and we looked at various examples of
the magnetic force. But in this chapter,
we're gonna ask the following question: What causes a magnetic field,
and how does it do that? Well, we
know
from the previous chapter from Oersted's
experiment
that an electrical current
or a moving electrical charge
can cause a magnetic field but we didn't address how this is done.
What kind of, given a current or given
a charged particle,
what kind of magnetic field can it produce?
This is the question answered in this chapter.
So, electrical current causing a magnetic field
but exactly how does it do that?
We can focus on a single moving charge, or we can focus on
a segment of the current.
Each single moving charge in the segment
current will produce its own magnetic field.
So if you look at an infinitely long segment
there will be an infinite number of charge carriers
each producing a magnetic field that could lead to an infinitely large "B" field.
What we're going to do is isolate an infinitesimally small segment
of the current out and look at how this small
segment
can produce a magnetic field, and later
on if you wanna know
the magnitude at this point coming
from all segments
on the current all you have to do is to add the
contributions up
by the superposition principal
We're going to isolate this little current element.
It is analogous to
a single point charge producing
an electric field. We want to know:
how does this element of current produce
a magnetic field at a point P?
In the case of electric fields, the source was just a point charge
and all we had to know was where it is
and the amount of charge Q, but this time we have a
current element. Now not only do we have to know where it is,
you know, vector displacement between the
source
and the point of interest, we also have to know the orientation of this element
because it makes a difference when a current flows
in one way or another.
We have here, a vector ds which is the
displacement vector from the beginning of the element to the end of the element.
A current flows along ds and ds
is along the direction of the current flow.
We want to know: what is the magnetic field at point P?
This magnetic field is infinitesimally small because it is produced
by infinitesimally small segments
So we're looking for dB. What is dB equal to?
dB is a vector that depends on two other vectors. One is ds and the other is r.
We've seen something like that
before in the previous chapter.
The magnetic force
exerted on a movie charge was a
function of two
other vectors, one was the
the velocity of the moving charge and the
other was B, the magnetic field.
We argued by symmetry
at that time that the resultant vector F, the
magnetic force, has to be perpendicular
to both v and B.
Now in our case, we have a magnetic field dB
which depends on two factors: ds and r.
Can we make a similar argument
to indicate a direction of dB? It turns
out,
yes, we can do that. The argument is totally
analogous to what we did in the previous chapter.
Basically reverse ds and r and see what happens, and that is equivalent to rotating the whole thing by
180 degrees and so on, so forth.
You can do that argument yourself and you'll
find
that because of symmetry the magnetic
field at point P
has to be perpendicular to both vectors ds and r.
In other words, it will be in direction ds x r
or r x ds. Which one do we pick?
That is entirely due to convention, it's how we define
the magnetic field, the positive direction magnetic field.
It's not a surprise to see that
dB is proportional to ds x r
as far as the direction is concerned.
Also, it's easy to understand the magnetic
field should be
proportional to the current because if I
double the current, then I have twice as
many moving charges here.
Each can produce a certain amount of magnetic field here
so the value of dB will be doubled.
So, it is proportional to I.
Another thing, how does it depend on distance?
In the case of Gauss' law,
we know that it is an inverse square of Coulomb's law that makes Gauss' law unique
so in the case of an electric field produced by point charge,
the field goes down by 1/r^2, the famous inverse square law.
Do we have the same situation here? Well
electricity and magnetism, they go hand-in-hand
so it is still quite easy to
understand, at least quantitatively, that we have the same
inverse square law here for for the magnetic
field as well.
It also is going to be over r^2.
We didn't derive this but we just try to
make it sound plausible, that's all.
So it turns out dB is equal to Ids x r over r^2
and this r, as you see, with this "cap", it is only
the unit vector, which has magnitude of one.
So it's 1/r^2 as far as distance is concerned.
To make it equal we have to deduce a constant "K"
and that K has to use magnetism, not electricity so we use a subscript "m"
to indicate this has to do with a magnetic field.
That completes the expression for dB.
This expression tells us how to find
a magnetic field
of a current element. It is analogous the Coulomb's law
which tells how to find the electric field
produced by
a point charge. So we use a current element
to replace an electric charge in producing a magnetic field.
And here, this k_m,
is equal to exactly 10^-7 Tesla times meter over amp.
The units are quite straightforward to understand because you have to balance the units on both sides.
Here is Tesla,
and here is a meter and a meter squared so overall there's a meter going over
and then I, which is amp, goes down like that.
Now why is it equal to exactly 10^-7? No more, no less?
Well, it's because how we define Tesla, see Tesla is a new unit
and the way we defined Tesla
is based on the choice of this constant K
so we could choose the constant K to be any value we want, we can even choose it to be 1.
But that was not the convention people adopted.
And just like the case where, in the Coulomb's law, you have k_e which is defined as
1/(4*pi*epsilon-naught), remember that?
Here we also define k_m as another constant mu-naught over 4pi
and that mu-naught, of course, that becomes 4pi * 10^-7
in SI units, and it is called the "permeability
of free space", so there is a fundamental
constant here
mu-naught, given that we could find k_m.
So we have two fundamental constants we
learned so far
in physics 1C. One was epsilon-naught,
that is for electric field. The other is mu-naught, that's for the magnetic field.
We'll come back to these two constants
later and we'll see how we can combine them to
do something magical.
But let's go back to this formula.
This is, again, analogous to Coulomb's law.
It has the same importance in the
calculation magnetic field as Coulomb's law is
to the case of the electric field. It is called the Biot-Savart law.
And again, the electrical charge in the case of Coulomb's law is replaced
with the current element.
Now this is only the alleged
magnetic field produced by a current element.
What if you have
a finite length segment, say, from here to there.
What is the total magnetic field produced by this entire segment?
Well, remember we went from a single point charge
to a bunch of charges in any charge distribution?
The key was to use the so-called "linear superposition" principle.
It turns out the same principle
applies here in the case of a magnetic field
which means if you have a whole bunch of
current elements, not just one, then
the superposition principle says that
you can calculate dB created by each element as if the
other segments do not exist, just like this,
and then all we have to do is add them up linearly so just
db1 + db2 + db3 and so on. You'll get a total magnetic field.
So, again, the same linear superposition principle applies to the B field,
not just the E field.
In other words, B of a finite current distribution, is just the sum over dB
Just the sum over dB. You just sum the
contribution from every current element of the entire source.
That's how you go from a current element to any current distribution.